{
  "reference_number": "9250",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The Ministry largely uses IPCC guidelines. There is however a significant body of scientific opinion which holds that the IPCC approach\n does not take adequate account of several factors including melting of Antarctic ice. In this case adverse effects of climate change\n\n may bite harder and faster than anticipated. There is a very good case for setting an earlier target date for zero carbon such as 2040."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "While methane is relatively short-lived in the atmosphere, its greenhouse effect is stronger than carbon dioxide, so it is essential that\n we include this gas in the plan. This is especially important (though difficult) for New Zealand to do."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "While it may be tempting to ease our position by buying credits from overseas, this process has been so discredited that I would not\n\n want to make this an option for government. I would like to see New Zealand set an example for other countries to follow, and this\n would be one way of doing so."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "If as many scientists fear the position is worse than IPCC figures suggest, it would be sensible to allow for the tightening or bringing\n\n forward of the emissions reduction process. I can’t imagine any situation in which we would all be better off by loosening the targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is important that the budget periods be longer than the average lifetime of government."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "Similar proviso as above. There should be the flexibility to tighten the budget if need be, but not to slacken it."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "See the climate change papers published by Engineers for Social Responsibility at www.esr.org.nz . It will be essential to liaise with\nlocal governments which will carry much of the frontline responsibility."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "I’m ok with ‘advise’ provided that the dialogue between Commission and Government is published for all to see."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Not sure whether adaptation is best covered in this or separate legislation. Either way, we need a clear plan for dealing with the very\nsignificant effects of climate change, some of which have been mentioned in the briefing document. We need to plan retreat from the\n\ncoastline, both for houses and industry but also for communication links such as SH6 and SH1 in the South Island. In the longer term\nwe need to look at large urban developments in central areas of both main islands."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Implementation needs to be carried out sensitively."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This is the biggest issue that we face, by far. It is essential that we join with other nations in reducing carbon emissions and preparing\n\nfor the climate change effects which are already inevitable. MPs need to know that they have our wholehearted support in tackling\nthese issues. They need to have the courage to take measures which may be unpopular in the short term, but are necessary for our\n\nlong term survival."
    }
  ]
}
